Rita and Daniel Fraad
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Rita and Daniel Fraad papers
1926-1997
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Fraad, Rita
3.3 linear feet
The papers of art collectors Rita and Daniel Fraad measure 3.3 linear feet and date from 1926 to 1997. The collection consists of art documentation files that reflect their American art collecting activities. Found in the files are any combination of the following materials: correspondence, sales receipts, treatment reports and photographs, loan agreements, facilities reports, exhibition and auction catalogs, clippings, photographs, transparencies, and slides.
Biographical Note
Rita (1915-2004) and Daniel Fraad (1912-1987) were American art collectors in New York, New York.
Rita (née Ritch) and Daniel Fraad were born in Brooklyn, New York, and met in their youth. Daniel graduated in 1935 from Brown University with a B.A. in biology and Rita graduated from Smith College in 1937 with a degree in political science. In 1938, Daniel joined Allied Maintenance Corporation (later Ogden Maintenance Corporation), a maintenance and cleaning services company started by his father in 1888. In the same year that Daniel joined the family business, Rita and Daniel were married. The couple eventually settled in Scarsdale, New York.
Rita and Daniel Fraad actively supported art institutions such as the Brooklyn Museum of Art, Metropolitan Museum of Art, National Academy of Design, and the Whitney Museum of American Art, among others. In 1965, the couple became members of the Archives of American Art and in 1989 Rita joined the Board of Trustees. She also sat on the Visiting Committee on American Art and Sculpture for the Metropolitan Museum of Art and was a member of the American Art Forum of the Smithsonian American Art Museum (SAAM). Rita was a SAAM commissioner for twelve years, and served as chair of the Collections Committee.
Over the years, Rita and Daniel Fraad amassed a museum-quality collection of American art which included works from George Bellows, William Merritt Chase, Thomas Cole, Jasper Cropsey, Arthur Davies, Charles Demuth, Marsden Hartley, Robert Henri, Winslow Homer, Edward Hopper, George Luks, Maurice Prendergast, John Singer Sargent, Everett Shinn, John Sloan, Joseph Stella, and James Whistler. In 1964, the Brooklyn Museum of Art, New York, organized an exhibition of the Fraad collection which traveled to the Addison Gallery of American Art, Phillips Academy in Andover, Massachusetts. In 1985, the Amon Carter Museum, Fort Worth, Texas also presented an exhibition of the Fraad collection.
Daniel Fraad died in 1987 and Rita passed away in 2004. In December 2004, the Fraad collection was auctioned at Sotheby's and raised over sixty five million dollars. The sale broke auction records; the amount was the highest total for any single owner's collection.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of art collectors Rita and Daniel Fraad measure 3.3 linear feet and date from 1926 to 1997. The collection consists of art documentation files that reflect their American art collecting activities. Found in the files are any combination of the following materials: correspondence, sales receipts, treatment reports and photographs, loan agreements, facilities reports, exhibition and auction catalogs, clippings, photographs, transparencies, and slides.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 1 series:
Series 1: Artwork Documentation Files, 1926-1997, undated (Boxes 1-4; 3.3 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Art--Collectors and collecting--New York (State)--New York; Art, American
Types of Materials:
Photographs
Names:
Fraad, Daniel
Provenance
The papers were donated in 2005 by Rita and Daniel Fraad via Jurate Nemickas, Fiduciary Administrator for the estate of Rita and Daniel Fraad.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Artwork Documentation Files1926-1997, undated, Series 1:; (Boxes 1-4; 3.3 linear feet)
  Artwork documentation files contain any combination of the following materials: correspondence, sales receipts, condition reports and photographs, loan agreements, facilities reports, exhibition and auction catalogs, clippings and magazine articles, photographs, transparencies, and slides.
  Files are arranged alphabetically by artist and by date of artwork. A file containing miscellaneous correspondence is located at the beginning of the series.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1971-1986, undated (Box 1)
  - Anshutz, Thomas, Two Boys and a Boat (1894), 1963-1985, undated (Box 1)
  - Ault, George C., Chimneys (1936), 1962-1968, undated (Box 1)
  - Bellows, George (Box 1)
    - Kids (1906), 1964-1995, undated (Box 1)
    - The Knock Out (1907), 1976-1995, undated (Box 1)
    - Shore House (1911), 1942-1943, 1972-1995, undated (Box 1)
    - Punching Tom and Pinching Mildred, The Embodiment of Good Nature (1912), 1976-1977, undated (Box 1)
    - Artists Judging Works of Art (1916), 1968, undated (Box 1)
    - Between Rounds, No. 1, Large (1916), 1968, 1981, undated (Box 1)
    - In the Park (1916), 1968 (Box 1)
    - Introducing the Champion, No.1 (1916), 1968 (Box 1)
    - Introducing John L. Sullivan (1916), 1968 (Box 1)
    - Preliminaries to the Big Bout (1916), 1968 (Box 1)
    - Study of Arms (1916), 1981-1983, undated (Box 1)
    - Training Quarters (Willard in Training) (1916), 1976 (Box 1)
    - The Sawdust Trail (1917), 1968 (Box 1)
    - Stag at Sharkey's (1917), 1972, 1992 (Box 1)
    - The Studio (1919), 1985-1995, undated (Box 1)
    - Study of Mabel (1919), 1961-1965, 1984-1985, undated (Box 1)
    - Tennis at Newport (1920), 1968, undated (Box 1)
    - Counted Out, No. 1 (1921), 1968 (Box 1)
    - Counted Out, No. 2 (1921), 1972 (Box 1)
    - Incident of the Ring-A Knock Out (1921), 1961, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Indoor Athlete No. 1 (1921), 1971, undated (Box 1)
    - Indoor Athlete No. 2 (1921), 1975-1983, undated (Box 1)
    - Introducing the Champion, No. 2 (1921), 1975 (Box 1)
    - Introducing Georges Carpentier (1921), 1968, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Marjorie, Emma, and Elsie (1921), 1968 (Box 1)
    - Old Billiard Player (1921), 1971 (Box 1)
    - Pool Player (1921), 1969, undated (Box 1)
    - The White Hope (1921), 1969 (Box 1)
    - Between Rounds, No. 2, Small (1923), 1968 (Box 1)
    - Dempsey and Firpo (1924), 1970 (Box 1)
    - Dempsey Through the Ropes (1924), 1975 (Box 1)
    - Jean in a Black Hat (1924), 1968 (Box 1)
    - Nude Study, Girl Standing on One Foot (1924), 1968 (Box 1)
  - Bishop, Isabel, Man Resting (1902), 1962-1968, undated (Box 1)
  - Blume, Peter, Timor II (1954), 1954-1968, undated (Box 1)
  - Bradford, William (Box 1)
    - Fishing Among the Icebergs (undated), 1985, undated (Box 1)
    - Fishing Shacks Beneath Cliffs (undated), 1985, undated (Box 1)
  - Buechner, Thomas S., Mintz Chicken Coop (1982), 1983, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Bunker, Dennis M., The Station (circa 1888), 1964-1996, undated (Box 1)
  - Burchfield, Charles, Wild Geese and Poplars (1956), 1958, 1969, undated (Box 1)
  - Chase, William Merritt (Box 1)
    - Landscape, Shinnecock Hills (circa 1989-1900), 1962-1994, undated (Box 1)
    - Multiple Portraits (undated), 1972-1979, undated (Box 1)
  - Cole, Thomas (Box 1)
    - Cedar Tree (1827), 1961-1962, 1988, undated (Box 1)
    - Study of a Tree (1827), 1964 (Box 1)
    - Study of a Tree (1827), 1964 (Box 1)
  - Coleman, Glenn O., Footlights (undated), 1963-1965, 1975, undated, (Oversized items housed in Box 4) (Box 1)
  - Cropsey, Jasper F., View from Nemi (undated), 1962-1968, undated (Box 1)
  - Davies, Arthur B., Nude in Landscape (circa 1905-1910), 1962-1969, 1984, undated (Box 1)
  - Demuth, Charles, Pepper and Tomatoes (circa 1927-1928), 1957-1985, undated (Box 1)
  - Dinnerstein, Harvey, Brownstone Doorway (undated), 1963-1964, undated (Box 1)
  - DuBois, Guy Pène, Paris Railroad Station (1925), 1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Duveneck, Frank, Portrait of Emil Carlsen (1884), 1959-1964, 1985-1988, undated (Box 1)
  - Eakins, Thomas, Study for Miss Emily Sartain (circa 1890-1895), 1957-1992, undated (Box 1)
  - Glackens, William (Box 1)
    - Yellow Bath House and Sailboats (1916), 1949, 1962-1964, 1985-1990, undated (Box 1)
    - Untitled (undated), 1958-1965, 1984-1985, undated (Box 1)
  - Graves, Morris (Box 1)
    - Crane (1954), 1958-1964, undated (Box 1)
    - Mountain Flowers (1957), 1972 (Box 1)
  - Hale, Philip Leslie, Study for Self Portrait (M.F.A. Boston; undated), 1966, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Hart, George, Theatre Interior (undated), 1961-1968, undated (Box 1)
  - Hartley, Marsden (Box 1)
    - Storm Wave (circa 1939-1940), 1955-1996, undated (Box 1)
    - Rocky Landscape, Dogtown Mass. (circa 1940), 1957-1988, undated (Box 1)
  - Hassam, Childe, Easthampton (1916), 1962, 1964, 1984, undated (Box 1)
  - Hawthorne, Charles (Box 1)
    - Little Dora (1915), 1957-1985, undated (Box 1)
    - The Morning Coffee (1918), 1952-1985, undated (Box 1)
  - Henri, Robert (Box 1)
    - Nursemaids (1898), 1967-1968, undated (Box 1)
    - Cumulus Clouds-East River (circa 1901-1902), 1958-1995, undated (Box 1)
    - Sylvester-Smiling (1914), 1961-1995, undated (Box 1)
  - Henri, Robert (Box 2)
    - Sketchers in the Woods (circa 1918), 1958-1994, undated (Box 2)
    - Concarneau (undated), 1964-1965, undated (Box 2)
    - Peasant Girl (undated), 1961, 1964, undated (Box 2)
  - Herschensohn, Arthur, The Lamplighter (1964), 1964, undated (Box 2)
  - Hirsch, Genevieve (Box 2)
    - Untitled (1950), 1964, undated (Box 2)
    - Untitled (1955), 1964, undated (Box 2)
  - Hirsch, Joseph (Box 2)
    - Eight Lithographs (1945, 1946, 1963, 1967, 1969), 1970, undated (Box 2)
    - Death of a Salesman (1948), 1961, 1968, undated (Box 2)
    - Inter-Office Souvenir Memo (1955), 1964, undated (Box 2)
    - Portrait of a Certain Tree (1955), 1964, undated (Box 2)
    - Portrait of Daniel Fraad Jr. (1955), 1964, undated (Box 2)
    - Portrait of Two Mud Trout (1955), 1964, undated (Box 2)
    - To the Big Man in the Little White Boat (1955), 1964, 1968, undated (Box 2)
    - A View from the Bridge (1955), 1961, undated (Box 2)
    - Smoking Fish (circa 1956-1957), 1957-1964, undated (Box 2)
    - Soup (circa 1957), 1957-1968, undated (Box 2)
    - Soft and Low (1965), 1965, undated (Box 2)
    - Rita at Work (undated), 1964, undated (Box 2)
  - Homer, Winslow (Box 2)
    - Green Apples (1866), 1962-1966, undated (Box 2)
    - Spring (1878), 1945, 1966-1997, undated, (Oversized items housed in Box 4) (Box 2)
    - Sand and Sky (1887), 1962-1964, 1983-1984, undated, (Oversized items housed in Box 4) (Box 2)
    - Prout's Neck in Winter (1892), 1956-1991, undated (Box 2)
  - Hopper, Edward (Box 2)
    - Man with Stick and Package (1901), 1972-1985, undated (Box 2)
    - Houses on the Beach-Gloucester (1923), 1956-1989, undated (Box 2)
  - Howes, John Townsend, Chimney Top Study (1892), 1965, undated (Box 2)
  - Inness, George, Barberini, Italy (circa 1871-1874), 1965-1978, undated (Box 2)
  - Johnson, David (Box 2)
    - Landscape (undated), 1968, 1979, undated (Box 2)
    - Landscape (undated), 1968, undated (Box 2)
  - Johnson, Eastman (Box 2)
    - Head of a Woman (circa 1849), 1940-1985, undated (Box 2)
    - Studies of Children (undated), 1961-1985, undated (Box 2)
  - Kamm, Richard, Mother and Child (undated), 1962, undated (Box 2)
  - Kensett, John Frederick, North Conway, 1851 (1851), 1961-1985, undated (Box 2)
  - Kuniyoski, Yasuo, Fisherman (1921), 1963-1965, undated (Box 2)
  - LaFarge, John (Box 2)
    - Pines in Snow (circa 1870s), 1963-1964, 1986, undated (Box 2)
    - A Taupo and her Duenna Awaiting the Approach of a Young Chief (1891), 1966-1991, undated (Box 2)
  - Lawson, Ernest, Horses Grazing by a Stream (1910-1920), 1962-1984, undated, (Oversized items housed in Box 4) (Box 2)
  - Levine, Jack, Inauguration II (1958), 1958-1990, undated (Box 2)
  - Luks, George (Box 2)
    - Cabby (New York Cabby) (1921), 1959-1986, undated (Box 2)
    - Old Schoolhouse, Ryders (1929), 1957-1971, undated (Box 2)
  - Marsh, Reginald, Railroad Yard (1929), 1968-1969, 1985, undated (Box 2)
  - McDermott, Untitled (undated), 1961-1964, undated (Box 2)
  - Melchers, Gari, Portrait of Mrs. George Hitchcock (undated), 1972-1993, undated, (2 folders; oversized items housed in Box 4) (Box 2)
  - Metcalf, Willard L., The Little White House (1919), 1963, 1965, 1984, 1995, undated (Box 2)
  - Meyers, Jerome, Paris Tuilleries (undated), 1961-1967, undated (Box 2)
  - Mora, F. Luis (Box 2)
    - Child Seated at Play (undated), 1965, undated (Box 2)
    - On the Shores of the Housatonic (undated), 1965, undated (Box 2)
  - Murphy, J.F., The Fence (Elizabeth, N.J.) (1879), 1962, 1964, undated (Box 2)
  - Noble, John, Cutting the Hay, Lake George (undated), 1963-1964, undated (Box 2)
  - Palmer, William, Patterns of Fertility (1957), 1957-1982, undated (Box 2)
  - Peto, John F., Library Table (undated), 1972-1985, undated (Box 2)
  - Potthast, Edward Henry (Box 2)
    - Beach Scene (circa 1915-1920), 1962-1964, undated (Box 2)
    - A Summer's Night (circa 1920-1925), 1962-1994, undated (Box 2)
    - Theatre Scene (undated), 1967-1968, undated (Box 2)
  - Prendergast, Charles, Still Life Panel (1936), 1963-1987, undated (Box 2)
  - Prendergast, Maurice (Box 3)
    - Venice (1898), 1963-1989, undated (Box 3)
    - Siena (1900), 1962-1992, undated (Box 3)
    - Circus Band (circa 1902), 1963-1997, undated (Box 3)
    - The Fountain (1909), 1926, 1962-1992, undated (Box 3)
    - Marblehead Rocks (1915), 1963-1990, undated (Box 3)
  - Robinson, Theodore (Box 3)
    - The Red Gown (1885), 1965-1988, undated (Box 3)
    - Drawbridge-Long Branch Rail Road (1894), 1962-1994, undated (Box 3)
  - Russell, John, Sleeping Man (1953), 1961, 1964, undated (Box 3)
  - Ryder, Albert Pinkham, Landscape (undated), 1955-1991, undated (Box 3)
  - Sargent, John Singer (Box 3)
    - Venetian Street (circa 1880-1882), 1964-1993, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Studies for Venetian Street Scenes (1882), 1971, 1983, undated (Box 3)
    - Group with Parasols (circa 1903-1911), 1961-1994, undated, (Oversized items housed in Box 4) (Box 3)
    - A Spanish Barracks (1906), 1963-1967, 1984-1985, undated (Box 3)
  - Sarka, Charles, Young Boy by a Banana Tree (1903), 1963-1967, undated (Box 3)
  - Shahn, Ben, Delinquents (undated), 1964, 1984, undated (Box 3)
  - Sheeler, Charles, Shaker Barns (1945), 1962, 1964, undated, (Oversized items housed in Box 4) (Box 3)
  - Shinn, Everett (Box 3)
    - Stage Scene (1906), 1963-1964, 1989, 1994, undated (Box 3)
    - Out of a Job-News of the Unemployed (1908), 1964-1985, undated, (Oversized items housed in Box 4) (Box 3)
  - Shirlaw, Walter, Weimaraner Sleeping (undated), 1965, 1968, undated (Box 3)
  - Sloan, John (Box 3)
    - Gray Day, Jersey Coast (1911), 1962-1964, 1983-1984, undated (Box 3)
    - Woman on Couch (1912), 1961-1965 (Box 3)
    - The Black Hat (1915), 1962-1964, undated (Box 3)
  - Speicher, Eugene, Woman's Head (undated), 1964, 1967, undated (Box 3)
  - Stella, Joseph, Pittsburgh Winter (1908), 1963-1994, undated, (2 folders; Oversized items housed in Box 4) (Box 3)
  - Sully, Thomas, Lady Seated at Writing Table (undated), 1964-1965, 1979, undated (Box 3)
  - Thomason, R.S., Untitled (undated), 1968, undated (Box 3)
  - Tonnicliffe, Charles F., R.A., Multiple Prints (undated), 1986, undated (Box 3)
  - Twachtman, John Henry, Gloucester, Fishermen's House (1900), 1967-1968, 1984-1987, undated (Box 3)
  - Waldo, Samuel Lovett, Portrait of a Gentleman (undated), 1964, undated (Box 3)
  - Webster, Herman, Fishing on the Pier (1878), 1964-1965, undated (Box 3)
  - Wending, Erwin, Flowerpiece (undated), 1961-1964, undated (Box 3)
  - West, Benjamin, St. Paul following the Viper into the Fire (undated), 1962-1971, undated (Box 3)
  - Whistler, James M., Seated Girl (1864), 1963-1984, undated (Box 3)
  - Whittredge, Worthington, Castel Gondolfo (1857), 1967-1968, undated (Box 3)
  - Coleman, Glenn O., Footlights (undated), 1963-1965, 1975, undated (Box 4)
  - Homer, Winslow (Box 4)
    - Sand and Sky (1887), 1962-1964, 1983-1984, undated (Box 4)
    - Spring (1878), 1945, 1966-1997, undated (Box 4)
  - Lawson, Ernest, Horses Grazing by a Stream (1910-1920), 1962-1984, undated (Box 4)
  - Melchers, Gari, Portrait of Mrs. George Hitchcock (undated), 1972-1993, undated (Box 4)
  - Sargent, John Singer, Group with Parasols (circa 1903-1911), 1961-1994, undated (Box 4)
  - Sheeler, Charles, Shaker Barns (1945), 1962, 1964, undated (Box 4)
  - Shinn, Everett, Out of a Job-News of the Unemployed (1908), 1964-1985, undated (Box 4)
  - Stella, Joseph, Pittsburgh Winter (1908), 1963-1994, undated (Box 4)